Register of the Vladimir Nikolaevich Bashkirov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vladimir Nikolaevich Bashkirov papers,
1909-1928
2002C26
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (2.0 linear feet)
Collection consists of correspondence, reports, and financial records, relating to Russian-American trade, and to Russian procurement of supplies in the United States during World War I and the Russian Civil War.
Bashkirov, Vladimir Nikolaevich, 1886-1969.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Vladimir Nikolaevich Bashkirov, a Russian-American businessman, was born in Samara, Russia. He started his career as a grain broker and developed into a successful industrialist. He was appointed Deputy Minister of the Provisional Government of the Russian Republic formed immediately following the abdication of Tsar Nicholas II. There he focused on the Imperial Russian government's efforts to procure much-needed military supplies in the American market before and after America's entry into World War I. After the collapse of Russia's Imperial and Provisional governments in 1917, Bashkirov went into exile in the United States and lived in New York. Bashkirov worked in the Division of Supplies of the Russian Embassy, where he coordinated and supervised purchases. Bashkirov was also a philanthropist, donating to the Tolstoy Foundation, the Literary Fund, and other Russian organizations.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of correspondence, reports, and financial records relating to Russian-American trade and to Russian procurement of supplies in the United States during World War I and the Russian Civil War. The bulk of the materials were gathered by Vladimir Nikolaevich Bashkirov during his time as a Deputy Minister of the Provisional Government of Russia and later in the Division of Supplies of the Russian Embassy in New York. Includes a substantial amount of correspondence with Boris Bakhmeteff (Bakhmet'ev), who was the only ambassador of the Russian Provisional Government to the United States.
Russia--Commerce--United States.; Russians--United States.; Soviet Union--Commerce--United States.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; United States--Commerce--Russia.; United States--Commerce--Soviet Union.; World War, 1914-1918--Economic aspects.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.
- Correspondence, 1917-1928
  - General, 1918-1927 (Box-folder 1: 1-7)
  - American Central Committee for Russian Relief, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Babcock, Frank M., 1920-1925 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Babson's Statistical Organization, 1921-1923 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Bagrationoff, P., 1921-1923 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Bakhmeteff (Bakhmet'ev), Boris Aleksandrovich, 1919-1926 (Box-folder 1: 12-21)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes financial documents.
  - Balmont, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Bashkirov, Aleksandr N., 1921 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Bashkirov, Kirill Aleksandrovich, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Baulin, Iakov Aleksandrovich, 1920-1926 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Berelovich, Iakov L'vovich, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Biranoff, Andrei Aleksandrovich, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Blodgett Milling Co., 1921 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Boehm, Andrew, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Borislavsky, Michael, 1924 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Borodin, D., 1926 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Bourmistroff (Burmistrov), A., 1922 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Breshko-Breshkovsky, Catherine K., 1919 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Bublikoff (Boublikoff), A. A., 1918-1920 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Central Executive Committee of the Russian Union of Peasants in the U.S. and Canada, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Central War Industrial Committee, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Chernyshev, S., 1924-1925 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Diky, Gregoire N., 1920 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - East European Trading Co. Inc., 1919 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Eroshkin, A., 1919 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Eugene H. Tower, Inc., 1920-1921 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Everett, E. V., 1920 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Executive Central Committee of the Federation of the Russian Organizations in America, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Fabian, C.F., 1918 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Gartz, Victor, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - General Committee of Russian National Defense, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Guaranty Trust Company of New York, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Herewith, Bary, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Iakovlev, S., 1927 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - John E. Thompson, Inc., 1922 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Jolles Shoe Company, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Kolesnikoff (Kolesnikov), Vladimir Nikolaevich, 1919-1927 (Box-folder 2: 14-15)
  - Kulagin, V., 1917 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Kuz'min-Karavaev, D., 1920 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Likhachev, Sergei Aleksandrovich, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Link Tool and Machine Corporation, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Lunts, Grigorii, 1919-1928 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - M.C.D. Borden & Sons, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Magalova, V., 1919 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Maksimov, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Malakhov, A., 1920 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Matoff, A., 1919-1920 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Melnikoff, N., 1920 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Moravskii, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Morozoff, K.I., 1919 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Mother (name unidentified), circa 1920 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Novoselov, Sergei Antonovich, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Olimpiev, Vladimir, 1922 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Orekhovie, Ivan Kondrat'evichie, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Pigott, William, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Rozenkovskii, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Russian Commerce Association of America, New York, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Russian Economic League, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - Russian Embassy, Washington, D.C., 1918-1920 (Box-folder 2: 37-38)
  - Russian People's Home in Brownsville, Inc., 1919 (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - Russian Remington Rifle Contract Trustees, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - Russian War Sufferers' Relief Society, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - Russkoe Tekhnicheskoe Obshchestvo na Blizhnem Vostokie, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - Samoilov, A., 1919 (Box-folder 2: 43)
  - Shatrov, I. A., 1919 (Box-folder 2: 44)
  - Sikorsky (Sikorskii), Igor, 1929 (Box-folder 2: 45)
  - Skvortsov, M., 1918 (Box-folder 2: 46)
  - Sokoloff, Andrei, 1922 (Box-folder 2: 47)
  - Tarnovskii, Adam, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 48)
  - Travelers insurance companies, 1923-1927 (Box-folder 2: 49)
  - Uget' (Ughet), Sergei S., 1920-1928 (Box-folder 2: 50)
  - Umoff, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 51)
  - United States Lines, 1922 (Box-folder 2: 52)
  - United States Mail Steamship Company, Inc., 1921-1927 (Box-folder 2: 53)
  - United States Tobacco Co., 1920 (Box-folder 2: 54)
  - Volkov, A., 1919 (Box-folder 2: 55)
  - W.P. Tanner-Gross & Company, Inc., 1921 (Box-folder 2: 56)
  - Znamenskii, Ivan Gerasimovich, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 2: 57-58)
- Subject file, 1909-1923
  - Ministerstvo prodovol'stviia (Ministry of Food), 1909-1921
    - Russia's and other countries' crops and agricultural production reports, 1909-1918 (Box-folder 3: 1-3)
    - "Privoz v Rossiiu v 1913 godu po gruppam," export sales (Box 3: 4)
    - Izvestiia po prodovol'stvennomu delu, bulletin, No. 2 (33), June-July, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Manchzhurskaia ob"edinennaia zakupochnaia uprava, directives, reports, and meeting minutes, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Directives for inspectors assigned to business trip to Siberia, 1917-1918 (Box 3: 7)
    - Trading with Russia, reports, statistical data, and contracts, 1917-1921 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Rossiiskii Finansovo-Promyshlenno-Torgovyi Soiuz v Parizhe (R.F.P.T.), (Russian Financial, Industrial and Commercial Association in Paris) files, 1921-1923
    - "Spravochnyi listok soiuza,", 1921 (Box-folder 3: 9-12)
    - Activity reports, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 3: 13-14)
    - Reports to the New York branch, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - Meeting minutes, 1921-1923 (Box-folder 4: 1-6)
      Includes London office meeting minutes.
    - Declaration and appeal, 1922 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - "La reprise des relations économiques avec les soviets,", 1922 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - "Biulleten' informatsionnago otdela,", 1922-1923 (Box-folder 4: 9-12)
  - Soiuz Sibirskikh Maslodel'nykh Artelei i Drugikh Kooperativov (Union of the Siberian Creamery and Other Co-operative Associations), 1918-1920
    - Trade proposals, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - New York branch trading reports, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 5: 4-10)
    - Contracts with United Sates government, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 5: 11-12)
    - Shipping reports, 1919-1920 (Box 5: 13)